本片改编自2006到2011年间
发生在威尔士彭布罗克郡的真实警方调查
为了戏剧化的效果以及适当地保护匿名性
剧中的部分人物和事件有所改动
二  一
'..two, one.'
晚上好  我们正在彭布罗克郡直播
Good evening. We are live in Pembrokeshire,
在这里  威尔士两起最棘手的案件
where there have been dramatic developments
有了巨大进展
involving two of Wales' most baffling crimes.
几十年过去后  警方现将重新调查这两宗双尸案
Decades on, these two double murders are being reinvestigated.
史蒂夫·威尔金斯警司
Detective Superintendent Steve Wilkins
是这次重新调查的负责人
is the man leading this reinvestigation.
DNA分析技术的发展彻底改变了
Developments in DNA analysis have revolutionised
对悬案的复审方式
'cold case reviews.
我们团队应用这些技术
'As a team, we have brought these processes
来协助侦破这两起案件
to bear on these 'two investigations,
目前已发挥了巨大作用
and they have had a significant impact.'
你认为是同一个本地男子犯下了
'And do you think it's the same local man responsible
-这四宗谋杀吗  -没错  乔纳森
- 'for all four murders?' - 'I do believe that, Jonathan.
多亏有先进的DNA取证技术
'Thanks to the advances in DNA forensic science,
我们现在更有可能
'we are now in a much stronger position
抓捕真凶
'to catch the person responsible.'
-满意吗  -还挺快的
- Happy? - That went quick.
-不赖吧  -嗯  谢谢
- Not so bad, was it? - No. Thank you.
彭布罗克郡谋杀案     第二集
囚犯情报员说
Prisoner Intelligence say
库珀现在最喜欢去的地方是图书馆
that Cooper's new favourite place is the library.
他专攻的方面  DNA
His specialist subject - DNA.
新闻报道起效了
The news item worked.
他担心我们有所发现
He's worried we've found something.
给日程里加个日子
Oh, a date for the diary.
达夫林监狱的典狱长
Dyffryn Prison's governor has given
给了我们面谈的日期
us our dates for the interviews.
一个月后
A month from now.
6月30日周一到7月2日周三
Monday, June 30th to Wednesday, July 2nd.
我们有三天时间  钻入他的脑子里
We've got three days to get inside his head,
找出那个让他夜不能寐的证物
find out the exhibits that give him night sweats.
兰博  我们该查查
Rambo, we should find out
是否有跟他对话过的
if there are any psychologists out there
心理学家  我想听听他们的看法
who have interviewed him. We want their insights.
好的
Right you are.
头儿  刚刚是彭布罗克郡港口警局
Boss, that was Pembroke Dock Police Station.
安德鲁·库珀昨晚被发现
Andrew Cooper was found collapsed
倒在了菲什加德外的铁轨上
by the railway tracks last night outside Fishguard.
他被送往了维瑟布什医院
He was taken to Withybush Hospital.
他自称服多了自己的止痛药
He claimed he overdid it on his pain medication.
在铁轨旁吗
By the railway tracks?
据说  他坚称自己并没有想自杀
Apparently, he's adamant he wasn't trying to kill himself.
他今早已经出院了
He checked out of the hospital this morning.
企图自杀吗
Tried to kill himself?
他可没有很努力  他还活着呢
Didn't try very hard, did he? He's still breathing.
-约翰  -对了  你猜怎么
- John... - Anyway, guess what?
警察想找我谈话
The police want to interview me.
新闻上的报道  我就是他们的嫌疑人
That stuff on the news. I'm their bloody suspect.
-为什么是你  -跟之前一样  是吧
- Why you? - Well, it's the same as before, hm?
因为陷害无辜的人
Cos it's easier to frame an innocent man
比认真工作要容易
than it is for them to do their job.
你最好小心点  他们可能会想找你谈
Now, you'd better be on your toes. They might wanna talk to you.
找我谈
Talk to me?
谈什么  我什么都不知道
What about? I don't know anything.
等他们找来  你就这么说
When they come knocking, that's exactly what you tell them.
你可别因为同情
And don't go running off to Adrian
就跑去找阿德里安  他是告密鬼
cos you feel sorry him. He's a rat.
你对他说的话  会被他直接捅给警察
And anything you say to him will go directly back to the police.
我来了
I'm coming!
你好  安德鲁
Hello, Andrew.
你好
Hello.
抱歉打扰  听说你刚从医院出来
Sorry to bother you. I heard you'd been in hospital.
你还好吗
How are you doing?
我很好
I'm fine.
我就想告诉你
Well, I just wanted you to know
如果你觉得你需要支持
that if you feel like you need some support,
我们可以帮你
we can sort something for you.
我不需要那个
I don't need anything like that.
你不用担心我
You don't have to worry about me.
哈利·斯蒂芬斯博士
Dr Harry Stephens...
是利物浦大学的鉴证心理学家
..is a forensic psychologist from Liverpool University.
他为一本关于暴力罪犯的书采访过库珀
Now, he interviewed Cooper for a book about violent offenders.
他是唯一公开表示
He's the only person to have gone on record
库珀是冷血精神病的人
as saying that Cooper is a psychopath.
他还跟我们说
He also told us that,
就像大部分冷血精神病那样  库珀是个自恋狂
like most psychopaths, Cooper is a narcissist
我们也该据此调整对他的态度
and we should treat him accordingly.
把他捧上天
Like royalty.
哄他  让他产生虚假的安全感
Er, pamper him into a false sense of security.
奈杰  找个合适的警局做面谈
Nige, we need you to find a suitable station for the interviews.
朴素  干净  安静的拘留室
Sterile, clean, quiet holding cells.
并确保守卫警官非常可亲
And make sure the custody sergeant is very charming.
是  头儿
Yes, boss.
斯蒂芬斯博士还建议
Dr Stephens also recommended
面谈团队中得有个女人
that one of the interview team be a woman.
对  据说  库珀很瞧不起
Yeah, apparently, Cooper has a very
女性的智力
low opinion of female intelligence.
如果他对面有女人  可能会让他放松警惕
And a woman opposite him might make him drop his guard.
-你能行吗  姑娘  -让我去吧
- Are you up for that, missus? - Let me at him.
那就这样  你和兰博去
That's settled, then. You and Rambo in the room.
-你呢  头儿  -那恐怕不明智
- What about you, boss? - I don't think it's clever.
我们知道他在电视上看到过我
We know he's seen me on TV.
我是调查的门面人物
I'm the face of the investigation.
可能会让他不安
That could rattle him.
我还是和你们一起坐在后排看监控吧
No, I shall sit in the cheap seats with you lot on video link.
那就敬我们的面谈团队
Hey, here's to our interview team, then.
猛男兰博[《第一滴血》]和花瓶宾博
Rambo and Bimbo.
约翰  我再问你一次
'I'll ask you again, John.
彼得和格温达·迪克森被谋杀
'Regarding the murders of Peter and Gwenda Dixon,
是不是你做的
'were you the person responsible?
他一开始很配合
He starts off cooperative.
但当你的人开始采取高压手段
Then, when your man gets heavy-handed,
他就闭口不谈了
down comes the portcullis.
那我们就不要咄咄逼人
So, we keep it non-confrontational.
甚至避免直接询问有关谋杀的任何问题
Er, maybe even avoid any direct questions about the murders.
如果不提谋杀
If we can't talk about the murders,
我们怎么从他那得到有用信息
how are we supposed to get anything useful out of him?
提证物
You talk about the exhibits.
这才是重点
That's what this is all about,
试着套出他最担心的是什么
trying to draw out which ones he's worried about,
看他认为哪件证物
which ones he thinks might
可能会留下他或受害者的DNA
bear a trace of his or his victims' DNA.
杰克
Jack?
某人挺积极嘛
Someone's keen.
我要参加郡队的选拔赛
I've got a trial for the county.
不是吧
No way!
太棒了
Ah, that's great.
好样的  小威尔金斯
Well done, Wilkins Junior!
你能来吗
Do you think you can come along?
-算了吧  没事  -不不不
- No, it's OK. - No, no, no.
胡说什么呢  我一定去
Bollocks. I'll be there.
真不错  儿子
Well done, son!
-吃东西去  -好
- Food? - Aye.
走吧
All right?
嗯
Yeah.
我们在阳光明媚的阿曼福德见
I'll see you in sunny Ammanford.
史蒂夫·威尔金斯
Steve Wilkins.
头儿  这里是指挥部
'Hello, boss, this is Control.
库珀已经离开达夫林监狱
'Cooper has left Dyffryn Prison.
预计9点抵达阿曼福德
ETA Ammanford 09:00.
他们都准备就绪  就等你了
They're all set up for you.
我去厨房带了杯喝的  头儿
I found the kitchen, boss.
谢谢
Thanks.
你好
Yep?
他来了
He's here.
早上好  约翰
Good morning, John.
旅途还愉快吧
'I hope you had a comfortable journey.'
当然了
'Oh, yes.'
商务舱
Business class.
你看  礼貌点又不要钱  是不
See, it doesn't cost anything to be polite.
他上钩了
He takes the bait.
他变老了
He's old.
但看着还是很强壮
He still looks strong, though.
开始了  头儿
All right, boss.
早
'Morning.'
早上好  约翰
Good morning, John.
电视上的那个大人物哪去了
Where's the big cheese, then, the one off the telly?
威尔金斯警司不会参与我们的面谈  约翰
Detective Superintendent Wilkins won't be joining us, John.
他喜欢在一旁看戏  是吗
Oh, he likes to watch, does he?
好了  约翰
OK, John...
1978年
1978.
你赢下了《找到那个球》
'The year you won Spot The Ball.
9万4千镑奖金
£94,000.
放在今天大约是80万镑
'That's about £800,000 in today's money.
你当时过着优渥的生活
'Your life was good at the time.'
你在玫瑰市场镇买下了大农场
You bought Big House Farm at Rosemarket.
你妻子告诉猎人行动的调查组
Your wife told Huntsman
你还带你兄弟和其家属去了西班牙
you also took your brothers and their families to Spain.
-是这样没错  -你没带上阿德里安
- I certainly did. - You didn't take Adrian.
为什么  约翰
Why was that, John?
我不知道
I don't know.
可能是他当时犯了哮喘
Maybe he was ill with his asthma.
你们不是一直在和他联系吗
You've been talking to him, have you?
没有  约翰
No, John.
我们有他给调查组留下的口供
We have his statements from Huntsman.
话说  约翰
So, John...
当时一切都很顺利
things were going well.
你那段时间一直在炒房
You were buying and selling properties.
但之后你开始为钱发愁
But then the money worries started.
一个房产经纪人骗了我一大笔钱
Well, an estate agent tricked me out of a lot of money.
我的事务律师对我撒了谎
My solicitor lied to me.
当你赚了一点钱时
When you come into a bit of money,
就会引来一群觊觎的蟑螂
well, the cockroaches come out of the woodwork.
从拥有自己的大农场
It can't have been easy,
到在玫瑰草地巷28号租房
moving from Big House Farm, making the adjustment
这个转变你肯定不容易接受吧
from owning your own place to renting at 28 Rose Meadow Lane.
男人不会自怨自艾
A man doesn't sit around moping.
而是会想办法改变现状
He's got to get out there, got to get grafting.
从1978年到1983年
Between 1978 and 1983,
你花了超过12万5千英镑
you spent over £125,000.
比你在《找到那个球》赢的奖金还多3万5千英镑
That's £35,000 more than your winnings on Spot The Ball.
要想赚大钱  就得承受一些风险
Well, you've got to speculate to accumulate.
你就是从那时起开始赌博的吗
Is that when you started gambling?
每周就那么三四英镑
What, £3 or £4 a week?
玩玩50镑一次的三选一
A £50 round robin?
这不能叫赌博吧
I'd hardly call that gambling.
阿德里安告诉调查组你一场比赛就下了一千镑赌注
Adrian told Huntsman you bet £1,000 on one race.
他记错了
He misremembered.
1983年  4月20号
April 20th, 1983.
弗雷斯特洛普的克莱斯顿公寓
Clareston Hall, Freystrop.
你第一次被判入室盗窃罪
Your first conviction for burglary.
这就是你"改变现状"的方式吗  约翰
Is that your idea of grafting, John?
我不喜欢你的语气
I don't like your tone.
别不说话啊  约翰
Oh, don't shut down, John boy.
约翰
John...
如果你不想和我们说话  我们会尊重你
...if you don't want to talk to us, we'll respect that.
你今天就可以回到达夫林监狱
You can go back to Dyffryn Prison today.
我不是贼
I'm not a thief.
做得好  兰博
Well done, Rambo.
你告诉猎人行动的调查组
'OK. You told Huntsman'
你在1984年8月
that you visited Scoveston Park
第一次去了斯科维斯顿公园
for the first time in August 1984,
跟理查德和海伦·托马斯见面
when you went to meet Richard and Helen Thomas
谈论在他们那里工作的事  对吗  约翰
about working on their land. Is that correct, John?
我知道阿德里安是怎么跟调查组说
I know what Adrian told Huntsman
斯科维斯顿公园的事的
about Scoveston Park.
说我叫他和他妈妈对警察撒谎
About me telling him and his mother to lie to the police
说火灾那晚我们一直在一起
about us all being in that night, the night of the fire.
据他说  事实就是
That the truth was, according to him,
我那天很晚才回家  身上一股焚烧的味道
that I came home late smelling of a bonfire.
你说你们没找他谈过  行吧
Now, you say you haven't spoken to him. Fair enough.
但有件事我想说出来
But there's something I want to get off my chest.
那男孩说的每句话
'Everything that comes out'
都是谎话
of that boy's mouth is lies.
自从我们没带他去西班牙后就一直撒谎成性
Has been ever since we didn't take him to Spain.
我和帕特回来之后
When me and Pat got back...
他就变了一个人
he was a different boy.
他变得暴躁
He was surly.
非常不听话
He was disobedient.
一直逃课
Bunking off school.
抽大麻
Smoking wacky baccy.
伪造支票  偷我们的钱
Forging cheques. Stealing money... off us.
这都是因为我们没带他去度假
And all because we didn't take him on holiday.
作为一个父亲
As a father...
这么说我一点都不高兴
I take no pleasure in saying this.
但事实的真相是  火灾和谋杀案发生的
But the truth is, the real truth, the night of the fire...
那天晚上
..the murders...
阿德里安才是晚回家的那个人
Adrian was the one who came home late.
他是在指控自己的儿子吗
He's pointing the finger at his own son?
人渣
Piece of filth.
我曾讯问过虐待妻子的人
You know, I've been across the table from wife-beaters,
强奸犯  恋童癖
rapists, paedophiles.
-结果我还是被他左右了情绪  -你起到效果了
- And I let him get to me. - And you made something happen.
当他感觉到威胁时  他就把锅甩给阿德里安
When he feels under threat, he blames Adrian.
这是值得注意的事
That's something to keep an eye on.
所以
So...
明天  猎人行动
tomorrow... Huntsman.
特别强调我们的主要证据
With particular emphasis on our prime exhibits.
给你们  好好看看
There you go, look at that.
约翰  我想问你关于一些证据的事
Now, John, I want to ask you about some exhibits
是猎人行动找到的
found by Operation Huntsman.
其中一些和一起抢劫案有关
Some of them pertain to one particular robbery,
就是你被定罪的萨迪斯抢劫案
the so-called Sardis robbery, for which you were convicted.
那是误判
Wrongly convicted.
录音存证  下面给库珀先生展示的照片是
'For the tape, I am showing Mr Cooper a photograph'
猎人行动库存证物BB-109  一只黑色手套
of Huntsman exhibit BB/109, a black glove.
约翰  你认得这只手套吗
Do you recognise this glove, John?
我不知道
I haven't got the foggiest.
昨晚我出了点小事故
I had a bit of an accident last night.
没有眼镜我什么都看不清  抱歉
I can't see a thing without them. Sorry.
我知道你们时间很紧
"I know you're on a tight schedule."
我们知道你在猎人行动时期眼镜就出了问题
We know you had a problem with your glasses during Huntsman.
我们从达夫林监狱拿到了你的度数
We got your prescription from Dyffryn Prison.
以防万一
Just in case.
我其实不戴手套
I don't actually wear gloves.
阿德里安才是家里爱戴手套的人
Adrian's the glove-wearer in the family.
录音存证  猎人行动库存证物MTJ-14的照片
For the tape, evidence photo of Huntsman exhibit MTJ/14.
黑头套
Black balaclava.
约翰  你认得这个黑头套吗
Do you recognise this balaclava, John?
你记不记得调查组在里面找到几根头发
Do you remember that Huntsman found head hairs inside it
经过法医鉴定后
that were forensically tested
证实了是你的头发
"and confirmed to be yours?"
是我的
Yes.
但你之前还说这不是你的
And yet you said it wasn't yours.
我记错了
That... was a mistake.
我说错了  这确实是我的
I was wrong. I think that was mine.
在监狱度过了十年  有的是时间仔细思考
Ten years in prison, a man gets into a lot of thinking.
他会想起很多已经抛到脑后的事情
He remembers things that he hasn't thought about for ages.
有一件事情我确实记得很清楚
And one of the things I do remember,
大概在20年前
and it was about 20 years ago,
我确实曾有过一顶黑色头套
was I did used to have a black balaclava
这个和我之前那顶一模一样
just like that one that I used to wear
我开自己的船去钓鱼时经常戴着它
"when I went fishing with a boat that I had."
想起了这个  其他事都顺其自然想起来了
"Well, remembering that, everything slotted into place."
对于这种情况  只有一种合理解释
There's only one explanation that makes any sense.
我的头套没有丢
I didn't lose the balaclava.
有人把它偷走了
It was stolen.
就是那个抢劫犯偷的
By the same individual who did the robbery
结果却怪在了我头上
"that I was wrongly convicted of."
好吧  约翰
OK, John.
我们继续
On we go.
猎人行动库存证物
Huntsman exhibits...
PAS-1  一把锯短的双管猎枪
"PAS/1, a sawn-off shotgun,"
还有证物PH-2
and PH/2,
一把锯短的双管猎枪  配定制的特殊肩带
a sawn-off shotgun with customised shoulder strap.
约翰  你认得这两把猎枪吗
Do you recognise these shotguns, John?
你想骗我
You're trying to trick me.
这把枪是我的
This gun is mine.
这把不是
This one is not.
调查组找到了这把枪  被油布包着
Huntsman found this gun, wrapped in oilcloth,
埋在你家的鸭笼下面
buried underneath the duck run at your home.
约翰  你为什么把它埋了
Why did you bury it, John?
我不想让阿德里安找到  怕他伤到自己
I didn't want Adrian to find it. Didn't want him hurting himself.
还有这把枪  PH-2
And this gun, PH/2,
和手套与黑头套一起埋在树篱下面
was found with the glove and balaclava under the hedge
就在萨迪斯村劫案发生地附近
close to the scene of the Sardis robbery.
我知道  调查组跟我说过几百遍了
I'm aware. Huntsman must have told me about a hundred times.
约翰  如果你仔细看
If you look closely, John,
你会发现两把枪都进行了同样的改造
you will see that both guns have the same modifications.
锯短的枪管  锯掉的枪柄
Sawn-off barrels and sawn-down stocks.
在枪管和枪柄上都有螺丝
Screws in both barrels and stocks
装上了肩带
"for a shoulder strap."
约翰  这两把猎枪上
"John, how do you account for the fact that"
如此独特的改造都一模一样
the very same distinctive DIY modifications
-对此你如何解释  -巧合罢了
- were made to both shotguns? - Coincidence.
世界之大  无奇不有  对吧
Stranger things have happened, right?
既然我们说到这个了
And while we're on the subject...
我想谈一谈
..I want to talk about
调查组在树篱下找到的那把枪
the gun that Huntsman found under the hedge.
录音存证
For the tape.
又来这一套
Here we go again.
在猎人行动审讯期间  我记得很清楚
"During the Huntsman trial, and I remember this very clearly"
因为当时我觉得特别奇怪
"because I thought it was very strange at the time,"
那位控方出庭律师
the prosecution barrister
不止一次把那把枪递给我
handed me the gun on more than one occasion.
我的意思是  如果那上面有我的DNA
Well, what I'm saying is, if my DNA is on that,
这就是原因
that's the reason why.
他在图书馆的时间可没白过
His time in the library was well-spent.
他在自掘坟墓
He's digging his own grave.
今天我们有很大收获
Today was a result for us.
他不遗余力地把自己与萨迪斯村
The lengths he went to to distance himself from
找到的证物撇清关系  说明我们正中要害
the Sardis exhibits means we are bang-on.
他说庭审时摸过那把枪
His story about the gun being handled in the trial.
黑头套在二十年前的1988年被偷
The balaclava being stolen 20 years before, in 1988,
也就是海岸小径案发生前一年
the year before Coastal Path.
他的说法不只告诉我们  偷头套的人
He wasn't just telling us the man who stole the balaclava
犯下了萨迪斯抢劫案
did the Sardis robbery,
他还证明了就是这个人杀了迪克森夫妇
he was saying the man murdered the Dixons.
今天他证实了我们一直所怀疑的
Today, he confirmed what we'd always suspected.
而且他给了我们新的线索
And he gave us something new into the bargain.
他杀害彼得和格温达·迪克森时
When he killed Peter and Gwenda Dixon...
戴着那个黑头套
he wore that balaclava.
而PH-2号证物毫无疑问就是杀人凶器
And PH/2 is, without a doubt, the murder weapon.
那我们要把哪些证物送回去重新检测  头儿
What exhibits shall we send back for re-testing, then, boss?
萨迪斯抢劫案的枪和黑头套
The Sardis robbery gun and the balaclava.
鸭笼那把枪就算了
Don't bother with the duck run gun.
把钱省下来干点别的吧
Save that money for something else.
那手套呢
What about the glove?
他说阿德里安才戴手套
He said Adrian was the glove-wearer.
这一定别有含义
That's got to mean something.
把手套也加上
Put it in.
我说完后别都立刻叫我蠢货
Don't all call me a twat at once...
蠢货
Twat!
但我们明知道检测结果会是不匹配的
..But what's the point in re-testing
重新检测还有什么意义
when we already know they'll come back negative?
检测残留DNA就像玩战舰棋  是个碰运气的游戏
Testing for trace DNA is like battleships. It's a guessing game.
检测员并不知道他们要找的是什么
The boffins can't see what they're looking for.
他们检测自己认为最有可能的微小区域
They test small areas they think are most likely
并期望有好的结果
and hope for the best.
但是总会有地方没被检测到
But there's always bits that haven't been tested.
那么
So...
明天就是我们审讯他的最后一天了
..Tomorrow is our last day with him.
我愿意冒点风险  和他当面对峙
I'm happy to risk a bit of confrontation.
兰博  我想让艾拉主谈
Rambo, I want Ella to lead.
好的
Right.
别把我晾在这啊
Hey, don't leave me hanging!
约翰  你觉得画像上的人
John, do you think the man in the drawing
和1989年7月时的你有任何相似之处吗
bears any resemblance to yourself as you were in July 1989?
没有  完全不像
No, not at all.
就连当时
Even the detective who
来家里的警探也这么说
came round the house said as much at the time.
里斯警员  以前常和你一起喝酒的那位
Detective Rees. The one who used to drink with you?
对
Yeah.
那约翰  1989年7月时你长什么样
So, John, how did you look in July 1989?
-你们没照片吗  -没有  约翰
- Haven't you got any photographs? - No, John.
所以如果你能帮我们  我们会很感激
Which is why we'd appreciate your help.
-我不记得了  都20年前了  -实际上是19年
- I don't remember. It was 20 years ago. - 19, actually.
对不起约翰  我就直说了
Sorry, John.  Let me get this straight.
你不记得你那时长什么样
You can't remember how you looked back then,
但你很确信那时候画的这幅画像
but you're confident that this sketch, made at that time,
"完全不像你"
'doesn't resemble you at all.'
我很确定
I'm sure.
因为我没留过那么长的头发
Because I know I didn't have hair that long.
你从没留过齐肩的长发吗
You never had collar-length hair?
我不喜欢头发扎到脖子
I don't like the way it feels on my neck.
画像里的人所穿的衣服呢  约翰
What about the clothes the man in the drawing's wearing, John?
我不穿短裤
I don't go in for shorts.
阿德里安比较喜欢短裤
Shorts were more Adrian's thing.
接着问短裤的事  艾拉
Stick with the shorts, Ella.
看见这人使用彼得·迪克森被盗银行卡的目击者
The witness who saw this man using Peter Dixon's stolen cash card
说他穿的短裤是卡其色的
said that the shorts he was wearing were khaki coloured.
你有过卡其色短裤吗  约翰
Did you ever own a pair of khaki shorts, John?
有过
Yes.
但那更像是泳裤长度的  而非短裤
But they were more bathers than shorts.
比画像上的要短  画里的短裤偏长
They were shorter than those. Those are long shorts.
我的短裤很短  接近泳裤长度
Mine were short shorts, more like bathers.
阿德里安那时比我更常穿这条裤子
Adrian used to wear them more than I did.
他总是借我衣服穿
He was always borrowing my clothes.
猎人行动在玫瑰草地巷28号
These are the only shorts that Huntsman found
只找到了这些短裤
at 28 Rose Meadow Lane.
没有卡其色的  并且都比
No khaki, and they're all a lot shorter
通缉令画像里的短很多
than the ones in the wanted photo.
那游泳裤呢
What about bathers?
他提了不止一次
He said that more than once.
泳裤  短裤  沙滩裤  长裤
Bathers. Shorts. Swimming trucks. Trousers.
我们全都查了
We did the lot.
他说那条短裤都是安德鲁在穿的
He said Andrew wore them.
他露馅了
That's his tell.
那条短裤让他感到担心
Something about those shorts worries him.
为什么
Why?
这条裤子到底在哪里
And where the hell are they?
帕特丽夏·库珀太太吗
Mrs Patricia Cooper?
我是史蒂夫·威尔金斯警司
Detective Superintendent Steve Wilkins.
这位是艾拉·理查兹督察
This is DI Ella Richards.
请问我们能进去一下吗
Can we come in for a minute, please?
请进
Come in.
你们什么都不会找到的
You won't find anything.
你们九年前就把约翰的所有东西都拿走了
Well, you lot took everything of John's nine years ago.
不是我们  库珀太太
Not us, Mrs Cooper.
你过去在奥基·怀特公司工作  对吗  库珀太太
You used to work at Ocky White's, didn't you, Mrs Cooper?
我曾是公司里最好的裁缝
I was the best seamstress they had.
这是你丈夫赢得《找到那个球》奖金那年拍的吗
These were taken the year your husband won on Spot The Ball?
1978年
1978?
-对吗  -是的
- Yes? - Yes.
一名专业摄影师来家里拍的
A professional photographer came to the house.
你有你们后来的照片吗  库珀太太
Do you have any later photographs of the two of you, Mrs Cooper?
没有
No.
我们不喜欢拍家庭照
We weren't big on family photos.
1978年  就是你去西班牙度假的那一年  对吗
1978, that was the year you went on holiday to Spain, right?
对
Yes.
冒昧问下  你为什么没带阿德里安一起去
Do you mind me asking, why didn't you take Adrian with you?
我不记得了
I don't remember.
你们问完了吗
Are you finished?
谢谢你
Thank you.
你怎么了
What's wrong with you?
警察来找过我
I had the police round.
问起你一条旧卡其色泳裤
Asking about an old khaki pair of bathers of yours.
这是怎么回事
What's that about?
-他们找到了吗  -没有
- Did they find them? - No.
你当年被捕时他们拿走了你所有衣服  你知道的
They took all your clothes when you were arrested. You know that.
你去联系一下阿德里安  看看是否在他那里
I want you to get hold of Adrian. Find out if he's got them.
我没他电话
I don't have a number for him.
雪莉的女儿是医院的接待员
Well, Shirley's daughter, she's a receptionist in the hospital.
她会告诉你电话号码的  你毕竟是他妈
She'll give it to you. You're his mother.
你是让我
You're telling me...
去跟阿德里安联系吗
to get in touch with Adrian?
是的
Yes!
鉴证部门说他们把肩带拆了  各个部分
Forensics said they took it apart, tested every nook and cranny,
每一寸都检测了
every millimetre of the shoulder strap.
他们还说重新检测上面的DNA
Yeah, they also said re-testing it for DNA
完全是浪费敬渥太华行动的钱和他们的时间
would be a complete waste of Ottawa's money and their time.
这不由他们决定
That's not their call to make.
我们的法医鉴定预算还有多少钱
Where are we with the forensics budget?
还剩1.7万镑
17,000 left.
总经费是3.5万镑
Out of 350,000.
天啊
Jesus...
老实说  头儿  我觉得
Honestly, boss, I'm not convinced
我们的钱没真正花在点子上
we're getting the best possible bang for our buck here.
我觉得我们该和盖洛普博士谈谈
I think we should have a sit-down with Dr Gallop.
确保我们不会被某个伦敦大案挤到一边
Make sure we're not getting sidelined by some big London job.
油漆下露出来的是金属吗
Is that metal I can see through the paint?
这里表面的漆磨损了
It's where the finish has worn off.
这把枪是上世纪40年代造的
That thing was made in the 1940s.
-漆是制造商刷的吗  -我们猜测是
- And that's the manufacturer's finish? - Yeah, we assumed.
-我们显然没亲眼见过这东西  -猜测
- Obviously, we've not seen the thing in the flesh. - Assumed?
真的吗  林恩  格林
Really, Lynne? Glyn?
猎人行动在库珀家有找到油漆吗
Did Huntsman recover any paint from Cooper's home?
在工具棚里找到六罐
Yeah, six pots in the shed.
奈杰  把猎人行动工具棚的文件拿来
Nige, get the Huntsman shed file.
其中有黑色油漆吗
Any of them black?
有
Yeah.
JAW-100
Jaw/100.
Jaw/100...
把这个从仓库调出来
I want that taken out of storage.
你的小组调查该案已有18个月了
Your team have been on this case for 18 months now
总部
我们能找到的证据
and all we've got to show for it is
只有彼得·迪克森在一截绳子上的部分DNA
a partial for Peter Dixon's DNA on a piece of rope.
恕我直言  这种事我们经常见到
With respect, we're seeing this a lot.
过分执着于DNA  结果忽视了...
This obsession with DNA at the expense of...
其他没那么流行的分析方法
..Well, other, less fashionable avenues of analysis.
渥太华行动坚持要我们只关注DNA检测
Ottawa's insistence that we focus solely on DNA
使得我的团队无法施展
has put my team in a straitjacket.
不不不  我们是要求你们优先检测DNA
No. No, no, no. We asked you to prioritise DNA,
并没有排除其他方法
but not to the exclusion of everything else.
但我的同事们以为你就是这个意思
But that's the impression you gave my colleague.
盖洛普博士...
Dr Gallop...
如果让你们放手去做
..Let's say we remove the straitjacket.
情况会有什么不同吗
How would that change things?
那我们就能扩大搜索范围
Well, it would allow us to widen our search,
寻找其他类型的证据
look for other types of evidence.
我们一致认为凶手当时戴了手套  是吧
Now, we're agreed that the killer wore gloves, yes?
我们可以找织物纤维
We look for textile fibres.
纤维属于间接证据
Fibres are circumstantial.
-我们需要确凿证据  -是的  但是...
- We need hard proof. - Yes, but...
如果我们能找到足够的纤维
if we can find enough fibres
将犯人和受害者联系起来
linking culprit to victim,
同样可以有力描绘
it could tell an equally compelling story
犯罪情景
about the circumstances of the crimes.
甚至能帮你们跨过皇家检察署的起诉门槛
Maybe even get you over the charge threshold with the CPS.
好吧
Ok.
就这么做吧
Let's go for it.
好的
All right.
我们还有一个请求
We have one other request.
我们认为...
We believe...
这是海岸小径案的凶器
that this is the Coastal Path murder weapon.
是的  PH-2
Yeah, PH/2.
我听说了你让团队再检测一下
I heard you'd asked the team to have another look.
是的  但这次的请求不一样
Yes, but this is a different request.
猎人行动找到的物品之中
Among the items recovered by Huntsman
有一桶在库珀家工具棚发现的油漆
from the shed at Cooper's home
是安维林牌的750毫升装缎黑金属漆
was this 750ml tin of Anvileen satin black metal paint.
我认为库珀给枪管上了漆
I think Cooper painted the barrels of the gun
为了让枪在晚上不那么显眼
to make it less visible at night.
凶杀案发生在1989年
The murders were in 1989.
安维林直到1995年才开始生产这款油漆
Anvileen didn't manufacture this particular paint until 1995.
所以  如果PH-2是凶器
So, if PH/2 is the murder weapon,
油漆涂层下可能还找得到残留DNA
there could still be trace DNA under the paint.
已经过去6年多了
Well, that's more than six years.
在这期间枪可能被清洁过
During which the gun would've been cleaned,
被雨淋过  暴露在不同的天气环境中
rained on, exposed to the elements.
你确定把剩下的经费花在这上面是最明智的选择吗
Are you sure this is the best use of what's left of your budget?
我确定
I'm sure.
好吧
All right.
阿德里安·库珀
07700  900712
出售
2万英镑
可议价
喂
Hello?
你好  阿德里安
Hello, Adrian.
-喂  -你怎么知道我的电话号码
- 'Hello?' - How did you get my number?
听到你的声音我也很开心
Nice to hear from you, too!
你想怎么样
What do you want?
就是看看你过得如何
'Just to find out how you are.'
我听说你之前住院了
I heard you were in hospital.
你为什么要做那种傻事
Why did you go and do a silly thing like that?
根本没什么
It was nothing.
我只是不小心
'A mistake.'
我可以去看望你
I thought I could come and see you.
现在不太方便
It's not a good time.
我在装修
I'm doing the place up.
这里一团乱
'It's a bombsite.'
那就来我这吧
So, come to mine, then.
头儿  皇家检察署的奥利·韦克菲尔德来电找你
Ah, boss. Ollie Wakefield from the CPS called you.
好的
Great.
奥利  我是史蒂夫·威尔金斯
Ollie, Steve Wilkins.
听着
Listen...
渥太华行动需要你的帮助
Ottawa needs a favour.
达夫林监狱的监狱长
The governor at Dyffryn Prison
拒绝将库珀的第二次假释听证会延后
refuses to delay Cooper's second parole hearing.
皇家检察署说的话
'And I think a word from the CPS
应该能让他通融一下
might persuade the man 'to see some sense.
这个案子立不了  史蒂夫
The case, it isn't there, Steve.
你知道狱政处的人会说什么  没有确凿证据
You know what the prison services will say. No hard evidence.
-我也无能为力  -奥利  如果他被释放
- I'm sorry. - 'Ollie, if he is released'
回到社会上伤了人
back into the community and he hurts someone,
公众会把我们责骂得体无完肤
"Institutionally incompetent" will be a happy memory
到时我们就会怀念以前只被骂"体制性无能"了
'when we are up to our necks in public inquiries.'
你这么确信他还会杀人
You're that convinced he'll kill again?
他是连环杀手
He's a serial killer.
连环杀手不会...
Serial killers don't...
他们停不下来
They can't stop.
史蒂夫  不可避免的抱怨已经开始了
'Steve, inevitable mutterings have started.'
有人提出叫停渥太华行动
There's talk of shutting Ottawa down.
嗨  妈
Hi, Ma.
你的腿怎么了
What happened to you?
工作上出了事故
An accident at work.
自己安排好葬礼  就不用劳烦家人了
我想着你可能饿了
I thought you might be peckish.
你还去探望他吗
Are you still visiting him?
每周都去
Every week.
他出来后会跟你一起在这生活吗
Is he gonna live here with you when he gets out?
我是他妻子
I'm his wife.
他还能去哪生活
Where else is he gonna live?
他现在有点生气
He's a bit worked up at the moment.
警察又开始纠缠他了
The police are bothering him again.
是吗
Oh, yeah?
实际上
Actually...
这问题可能有点傻
it's a silly thing.
他的旧卡其色泳裤在你那吗
You don't have an old pair of khaki bathers of his, do you?
即使在监狱里  还在发号施令
Still running things, even from in prison.
我之前说工作中出了事故  那并不是真的
It wasn't true what I said earlier about an accident at work.
这是他造成的
He did this to me.
就是你们拍了那些破照片的那年
The same year you had those stupid photos done,
他弄伤了我的背
he broke my back.
他没有弄伤你的背
He didn't break your back.
一年前  我还很健康强壮
A year ago, I was fit and strong,
在爱尔兰工作  做建筑小工
working in Ireland, hod-carrying.
一天早上  我好像被闪电击中了一样
One morning, it was like I was struck by lightning.
做了整整九个小时的手术
Nine hours of surgery.
骨盆和脊椎里装上了钢钉和螺丝
Rods and screws in my pelvis and spine.
我本以为是工作造成的
I thought it was the work that caused it,
但是会诊医生告诉我是童年受的伤
but the consultant told me it was an injury from childhood.
我立刻就知道是我背上挨的那拳
Straight away, I knew it was that punch in the back.
你当时知道出了问题
You knew something was seriously wrong when it happened,
但你没带我去医院
but you didn't take me to the hospital
因为他担心有人可能会起疑
because he was worried someone might be suspicious.
我不知道那伤有那么严重
I never knew it was serious.
我根本不能动
I couldn't move!
你让我在自己的尿液里躺了五天
You left me to lie in my own urine for five days.
你都没换过我的湿床单
You didn't even change my sopping sheets.
但你给我买了很多吐司和草莓酱
You brought me plenty of toast and strawberry jam, though!
几周后  你们把我留给祖母照看
A couple of weeks later, you left me with nan
全跑去阳光灿烂的西班牙玩
and all took off for sunny Spain.
我当时才12岁
I was 12 years old.
我们想着你最好在家休养
We thought it was better that you rested.
你有什么毛病
What's wrong with you?
我不知道
I didn't know.
别走  阿德里安
Don't go, Adrian.
我给你打电话不是因为他让我打
I didn't just call you because he told me to.
我很想你
I've missed you.
第二次很幸运
Second time lucky.
我获得假释了
I got it?
恭喜  约翰
Congratulations, John.
你在圣诞节前就能出狱了
You're gonna be out by Christmas.
好样的
Well done.
是的
Yup. Well...
谢谢通知我
thanks for letting me know.
不敢相信他们现在要放他出来
I can't believe they're letting him out now.
我们差一点就成功了
We're so close.
真的吗
Are we, though?
我就当你是因为疲惫和今天不顺心才说这种丧气话
I'm gonna put that down to exhaustion and a shit day.
你知道我过完不顺心的一天后会做什么吗
Do you know what I do after a shit day?
什么
What?
我会回家
I go home...
然后跟家人一起吃大量的不健康食物
and I eat a large amount of unhealthy food with my family.
回家吧  史蒂夫
Go home, Steve.
陪你儿子
Be with your boy.
晚上好
Evening!
杰克
Jack?
我买了炸鱼薯条
I've got fish and chips!
我是杰克·威尔金斯  我暂时不方便接听
'Hey, it's Jack Wilkins. I'm not here at the moment.
有事留言  我会回你
'Just leave a message and I'll get back to you.'
终于回来了
Finally!
知道吗  要是你偶尔大发慈悲
You know, I'd appreciate it if, once in a blue moon,
接个电话或回个短信我就感恩戴德了
you'd answer your phone or responded to a text.
你是喝酒了吗
Have you been drinking, by any chance?
是  我去庆祝了
Yeah, I've been celebrating!
庆祝什么
Celebrating what?
我被选进郡队了
I made the county team.
谢谢你今天的"远程支持"了  老爸
Thanks for being there for me today, Dad!
该死
Shit...!
杰克
Jack!
别烦我
Leave me alone.
别跟我怄气
There's no need for that.
对不起  杰克
I'm sorry, Jack.
你信誓旦旦地说想让我们多在一起
You made such a big deal about us spending more time together.
但你根本做不到
But you just can't do it.
你太痴迷于工作了
You're so fucking obsessed with your work.
你个不负责任的老爸
You're a shit dad.
别这样  这么说不公平
Hey, now, come on. That's not fair.
听着  我很抱歉忘记了选拔赛
Look, I'm sorry I forgot about the trial.
抱歉我不是个完美的爸爸
I'm sorry I'm not a perfect dad.
这不是借口
It's no excuse.
我疏忽了  好吗
I took my eye off the ball, OK?
好吧
Ok.
你吃过了吗
Have you eaten?
吃了
Yeah.
那好
Right, well...
休息吧
get some kip.
这是我们最后的机会  各位
This is last chance saloon, guys.
库珀一周后就会回家
Cooper will be home in a week.
我们得重新梳理一切
We have got to go over everything.
没有能和警方绘制的画像
I mean, not having a photograph of Cooper
做对比的库珀的照片
that we can compare to the artist's impression,
是我们案件中的漏洞
it's a hole in our case.
奈杰  格林  去拜访他和帕特的亲戚
Nige, Glyn, doorstep his and Pat's relatives.
就说我们需要家庭照片  为了存档用
Tell them that we need family photographs for our records.
好的  头儿
Yes, boss.
我来开车
I'll drive.
安德鲁
Andrew...
那帕特呢
What about Pat?
他肯定得住在其他地方  对吧  她现在不能跟他住
He'll be housed somewhere else, right? She can't live with him now.
他们结婚很久了  安德鲁
They've been married a long time, Andrew.
如果他要对她动手  他早就做了
If he was gonna do something to her, he'd have done it by now.
你不能确定
You don't know that.
他坐了十年牢  谁知道牢狱让他变成什么样了
He's been in prison ten years. Who knows what that's done to him?
她还是很怕他
She's still scared of him.
我去看过她
I went to see her.
她打电话给我
She called me.
我还以为...
I thought...
我还以为她想母子重聚呢
I thought she wanted a mother-and-son reunion.
结果只是按他的话办事
But she was just following orders.
他叫她问我  他的旧泳裤是不是在我这
He wanted her to find out if I had an old pair of bathers of his.
这对你来说有意义吗
Does that mean anything to you?
你有吗
Do you have them?
我才不会穿他的衣物
I wouldn't wear anything of his.
去那边  杰克
Get down there, Jack!
加油
Come on!
角球
Corner.
好  去吧
Right, on it!
好样的  加油  儿子
Yes! Go on, son!
棒
Yes!
-球探今天又来了  -真的吗
- So, the scout was there again today. - He was?
他跟你说话了吗
Did he speak to you?
他说周末后给我打电话
He's gonna give me a ring after the weekend.
谢谢你今天来看我踢球  爸爸
Thanks for being there today, Dad.
客气了  宝贝
Oh, my pleasure, sunshine.
抱歉我之前疏忽了
I'm sorry I've been a bit of a pain.
别在意
Oh, don't you worry about it.
回见
Hey, I'll see you later.
-你不进来吗  -我最好别去了
- You're not coming in? - I'd better not.
是跟你的工作有关吗
Is it something to do with work?
-这是他以前常来的地方  -你开玩笑吧
- It's one of his old haunts. - You're joking?
我不该进去  有人或许会认出我
I shouldn't go in. Someone might recognise me.
那又如何
So?
我不希望别人把你和我联系到一起
Well, I don't want you connected to me.
只是以防万一
It's just a precaution.
没关系  我先进去就是了
It's fine. I'll go in ahead of you.
你不想看看里面吗
Aren't you curious to see inside?
你知道你想的
Come on, you know you want to.
算了  你进去吧  我一小时后来接你
It's fine. Go on, I'll pick you up in an hour.
麻烦给我一杯香蒂淡啤
A pint of lager shandy, please.
你们好啊
All right, lads?
打扰一下
Excuse me.
我是达费德郡警察
Dyfed Powys Police.
你知道照片里那男人是谁吗
Can you identify the man in the picture?
留八字胡那个吗  是约翰·库珀
With the 'tache? Aye, that's Johnny Cooper.
照片是什么时候拍的
When was the photograph taken?
我不知道  80年代末吧
I don't know, the late '80s.
估计是他上电视节目那段时间
Probably about the time he was on that...
叫什么来着  那个射飞镖机智问答节目
What do you call it? That darts quiz show on telly.
《正中靶心》  对  就是这个
Bullseye? Aye. That's the one.
1989年的《正中靶心》
Bullseye, 1989.
真的假的
You are shitting me!
库珀杀害迪克森夫妇那年
The year he killed the Dixons,
在全国性节目上射过飞镖
Cooper was throwing darts on national television.
就在ITV台
On itv!
我们一直在找这混蛋89年的照片
We've been looking for a photo of the bastard from '89.
现在没准能找到整段视频
And we might well have a whole bloody video.
老天
Jesus Christ...!
欢迎回家  亲爱的
Welcome home, love.
怎么了
What?
过来
Come here.
《正中靶心》是伯明翰的中央电视制作的
So, Bullseye was produced by Central Television in Birmingham.
但老节目的录像都存放在利兹的档案馆
But recordings of old shows are held in an archive in Leeds.
那边的管理员
Now, the librarian there
已经翻阅过80年代老节目的
has been going through lists of old contestants
参赛者名单
from old shows from the '80s.
第九季里
And in series nine,
能确认有两名参赛者
there's two contestants identified
来自南彭布罗克郡
as being from South Pembrokeshire.
他们参与的那期节目在89年10月播出
Now, the episode they were in was broadcast in October '89.
但录制是在5月28日
But it was recorded on 28th May.
比迪克森夫妇遇害时间早一个月零一天
A month and a day before the Dixons were murdered.
C1演播厅
-你拿到录像带了  -是的  刚送来
- So, you've got the tapes, then? - Yeah, they've just arrived.
欢迎收看《正中靶心》
'It's a bull's-eye!
有请主持人
'And here's your host...
-吉姆·鲍恩  -晚上好
- 'Jim Bowen!' - 'Good evening.
欢迎收看《正中靶心》
'Welcome to Bullseye.'
能快进到参赛者那部分吗
Can you just fast-forward it to the contestants?
很好  约翰  你有个不寻常的爱好
'Good. 'You've got an unusual hobby, John.
-是的  水肺潜水  -水肺潜水啊
- 'Oh, yes, the scuba diving.' - 'The scuba diving.'
那里是潜水的绝佳地点  不是吗
Apparently it's the place to do it down there, isn't it?'
-我们有很长的海岸线  -没错
- 'Well, we've got the coastline. - Yes.'
这是他声称从没留过的齐肩发型
And there's the shoulder-length hair he never had.
我们有深水区
'Well, we've got the deep water...
你也可以游过山脉之类的
'And you can swim over mountains and all sorts.'
希望大家都有个愉快的夜晚
'We hope you all have a good night.
给参赛者一点掌声鼓励
Give them a round of applause.'
祝好运  约翰
'Best of luck, John.'
5分
'That's five.
20分
'20.
1分  共26分
'And one. '26.'
36分  第一轮结束
'36, and takes the first round.
约翰  现在只有36英镑奖金  但也是一笔钱
'Right, John, it's only £36, but you really could do with this.'
你为什么泡澡
What are you having a bath for?
我很快就好
I won't be long!
-我可以和你一起泡  -不  约翰
- I could get in with you. - No, John.
-我害羞  -害羞
- I'm shy. - Shy?
你身上哪一寸我没看过
I've seen it all before, you know?
快点  老婆  让我进去
Come on, missus, let me in.
能按下暂停吗
Can you pause it there, please?
倒回去一点
Rewind a bit.
就是这里
There.
这也许不能证明他杀了迪克森夫妇
It may not prove he killed the Dixons.
但能证明他四周前长什么样
But it proves what he looked like four weeks before.
报警电话  你需要什么服务
'999, which service?'
在吗
'Hello?'
改编自史蒂夫·威尔金斯和乔纳森·希尔所著《彭布罗克郡谋杀案》